Harrison Smith Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harrison Smith papers
1904-1975
YCAL MSS 793
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.59
(13 boxes)
The Harrison Smith Papers contain writings, correspondence, printed material, and photographs that document the life and work of editor and publisher Harrison Smith, particularly his research on American author Sinclair Lewis, and his editorial work for the Saturday Review of Literature. Series I, Research Files on Sinclair Lewis, includes extensive biographical notes, presumably intended as the source material for a book-length biography of Lewis. Series II, Other Papers, consists chiefly of writings, interviews, and speeches that relate to the position of women in early- and mid-twentieth century society.
Smith, Harrison
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harrison Smith, 1983.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Harrison Smith (1888-1971)
Harrison Smith (Yale College 1911) was born Oliver Harrison Smith in Hartford, Connecticut on August 4, 1888. He received a bachelor's degree from Yale College in 1911, and a Master's degree in 1914. Smith's lifelong career in publishing began as an editorial assistant and textbook salesman, then eventually as an editor for Harcourt, Brace and Company (1918 to 1928). In 1929 he founded the firm Jonathan Cape & Harrison Smith, and went on to become a partner at Random House and an editor at Doubleday Doran & Company. From 1938 until 1966 he was president and associate editor of the Saturday Review of Literature. Smith wrote extensively on topics in American Literature, and on issues relating to working women and feminism after the Second World War. In 1952 he edited From Main Street to Stockholm, a volume of Sinclair Lewis correspondence.
Scope and Contents
The Harrison Smith Papers contain writings, correspondence, printed material, and photographs that document the life and work of editor and publisher Harrison Smith, particularly his research on American author Sinclair Lewis, and his editorial work for the Saturday Review of Literature. Series I, Research Files on Sinclair Lewis, includes extensive biographical notes, presumably intended as the source material for a book-length biography of Lewis. Series II, Other Papers, consists chiefly of writings, interviews, and speeches that relate to the position of women in early- and mid-twentieth century society.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Research Files on Sinclair Lewis, 1904-1962. II. Other Papers, 1935-1975.
Saturday Review of Literature; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Editors -- United States; Feminism -- United States; Publishers -- United States; Women -- United States; Photographs; Photographic prints; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Publishers -- United States -- 20th Century; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951; Smith, Harrison
- Research Files on Sinclair Lewis, 1904-1962; Series I; 3.96; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into eight subseries: Writings of Sinclair Lewis; Writings about Sinclair Lewis; Source Material; Sinclair Lewis Letters; Correspondence about Sinclair Lewis; Printed Matter by Sinclair Lewis; Printed Matter about Sinclair Lewis; Photographs.
  - Writings of Sinclair Lewis
    Scope and Contents
    Copies, proofs, and typescripts of writings by Sinclair Lewis, accompanied by editors' notes and related material.
    - Books and contributions to books, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Fools, Liars, and Mr. De Veto, proofs, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Page of notes in Lewis's handwriting, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Thirty-one early poems, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings about Sinclair Lewis
    Typescript drafts and copies of drafts of essays, interviews, and articles about Sinclair Lewis. Many of the typescripts are transcribed from printed versions.
    - Bish, Cora Frank, "The Sociology of Sinclair Lewis' Writings," a thesis, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fay, Oliver James, "I remember the author of Elmer Gantry", 1927 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Faikema, Feike, "In memoriam address", circa 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Habein, M. S., "The girl Sinclair Lewis couldn't forget", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Havighurst, Walter, "Homeless, restless Sinclair Lewis: Letters reveal a man of great gifts", 1952 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hawkins, Anne, "Worm's eye view of Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hughes, Rupert, "When Theodore Dreiser slapped Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Jackson, Joseph Henry, "Sinclair Lewis' letters", 1952 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Kay, Ida Lightman, "Sauk Center", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Manfred, Frederick Feikema, "Finger on the pulse...", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Manson, Alexander, chronological account of relationship with Lewis (interview), transcript, 1951 January (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Manson, Alexander, "The man from Main Street. A chronicle of the last days of Sinclair Lewis, as told to Helen Camp", undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Manson, Edith Hart, "Mary Austin and Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Nevinson, C. R. W., "From paint and prejudice", undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - New York Times Index, Sinclair Lewis. Copies of notes by a student, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Newsweek, "The Lewis letters", 1952 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Neilsen, Carl C., "Sinclair Lewis had his legs pulled", undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Random House, "The death of Sinclair Lewis", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Rathe, Chuck, "Sinclair Lewis burial", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Rogers, W. G., "Review. From Main Street to Stockholm", 1952 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Rowe, Dorothy Parker, "Sinclair Lewis' writing rules", undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Saltpeter, Harry, "Sinclair Lewis takes it easy", 1930 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Simpson, James Jay, "Estate of Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Smith, Harrison, "At the time he was notified of the award, Sinclair Lewis made the following statement...", 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Smith, Harrison, "A few months after the death of Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Smith, Harrison, "Jacques Barzun, teacher in America", undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Smith, Harrison, "Main Street looks at Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Smith, Harrison, Preface to "Our Mr. Wrenn", undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Smith, Harrison, "Sinclair Lewis", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Smith, Harrison, "Set not thy foot on graves", 1951 February 24 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Smith, Harrison, "We have heard the loud noise of history being made...", 1930 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Smith, Harrison, Review of "World so Wide" by Sinclair Lewis, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Warren, Dale, "God's lonely man", undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Waterman, Margaret, "Sinclair Lewis as teacher", undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Womer, M. Wayne, "Sinclair Lewis was my sailor", undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Notes, 1937, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Source Material
    - Sinclair Lewis chronology compiled by John Storck, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - List of correspondents numbered 1-998, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Guide to Sinclair Lewis notes, compiled by John Storck, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Survey of notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Notes in numerical order
      - 1-100, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - 101-200, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - 201-300, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - 301-400, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - 401-500, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - 501-600, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - 601-700, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - 701-800, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - 801-900, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - 901-1000, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - 1000-1098, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Notes in chronological order
      - 1904-1921 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - 1922-1926 (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - 1927-1939 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - 1940-1947 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Unordered notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 61-63)
    - Note cards, undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Sinclair Lewis Letters (copies)
    Copies of letters from Sinclair Lewis to named correspondents, accompanied by Harrison Smith notes and correspondence.
    - Baker, Gene, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Family, 1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Foerster, Norman, 1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Freeman, Lewis, letters dated 1925 to 1928, undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Jordan, Elizabeth, letters dated 1915 to 1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Mordell, Albert, letters dated 1925 and 1931, undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence about Sinclair Lewis
    Includes correspondence between Harrison Smith and named correspondents, copies of third-party correspondence relating to Sinclair Lewis, and related notes and clippings.
    - "A" General, 1932-1951 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Absolon, William, 1927, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Alpern, Vivian J., 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Arnold, LeRoy, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - "B" General, 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Bates, Roy C., 1951 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Bemis, H. Marion, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Bingham, Alfred M., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Bird, Remsen, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Blackman, Earl A., 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - The Boston Globe, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Breasted, Charles, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Brett, Ethel C., 1952 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Bull, Ben M., 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - "C" General, 1951-1956 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Cane, Melville, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Cary, Joyce (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Cassidy, George L., 1952 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Chase, Thurston, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - The Chicago Tribune, 1949-1954 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Clark, Charles Upson, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1936, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Commager, Henry Steele, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Conrad, Barnaby, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Couchman, Gordon W., 1953 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd., 1941-1952 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - "D" General, 1952-1960 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Dubois, Ben, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Dunne, Brian Boru, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - "E" General, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - "F" General, 1951-1956 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Fort, Mrs. J. C., 1951 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Freeman, Jr., Mrs. A. H., 1953 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Friedman, Philip Allan, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - "G" General, 1951-1953 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - "H" General, 1951-1953 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Habein, Margaret Schmitt, 1951-1953 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Harcourt, Brace & Company, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Hawley, Hudson R., 1951 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Heflin, Julia Dorn, 1951, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Holiday, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Hollander, Lester, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Hopkins, Frances, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Indiana University Press, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - "J" General, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Jelliffe, Belinda, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Josephson, Hannah, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - "K" General, 1951-1962 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Kastner, Harold, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - "L" General, 1931-1954 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - Larrabee, C. B., 1952 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Larrimore, Tom, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Lewis, Grace Hegger, (Mrs. Telesforo Casanova), 1951-1956 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Lewis, Virginia, 1954-1951 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Library of Congress, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - "M" General, 1951-1953 (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Malick, Elizabeth, 1951-1955 (Box 8, Folder 128)
      Includes photograph: "John Malick, Bethel, Ohio"
    - Manfred, Frederick F., 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - McComas, Gene, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Menninger, Karl A., 1952 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Miller, Mary E., 1952 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Mordell, Albert, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Moyston, Guy, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - "N" General, 1937-1956 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Nowell, Elizabeth, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - Oberlin Alumni Magazine, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - "O" General, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - Olmstead, John G., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - O'Neill, Dorothy, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - Otto, Mrs. Henry C., 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - "P" General, 1933-1953 (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - Palmer, George, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 143)
    - Parmelee, Maurice, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 144)
    - Peters, A. K., 1951 (Box 8, Folder 145)
    - Pfeffer, Max, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 146)
    - Poley, Irvin C., 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 147)
    - Pomeroy, L. A., Jr., 1945, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 148)
    - Porter, Keyes, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 149)
    - "R" General, 1947-1953 (Box 9, Folder 150)
    - Random House, Inc., 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 151)
    - Rich, Helen, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - Richmond, Sylvia B., 1941, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 153)
    - "S" General, 1951-1960 (Box 9, Folder 154)
    - Sandburg, Carl, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - Sheen, Vincent, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 156)
    - Shepard, Beatrice G., 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 157)
    - Sinclair Lewis Foundation, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 158)
    - Smith, Harrison, 1943-1947 (Box 9, Folder 159)
    - Staples, Loring M., 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 160)
    - Steichen, Kate, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 161)
    - Stevenson, E. Robert, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - Swing, Betty Gram, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 163)
    - Sykes, Velma West, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 164)
    - "T" General, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 165)
    - Thornton, William, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 166)
    - "U - V" General, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 167)
    - Updegraff, Allan, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 168)
    - "W" General, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 169)
    - Warren, Dale, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 170)
    - Werner, W. L., 1951, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 171)
    - Willoughby, Betty Cass, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 172)
    - W. W. Norton and Company, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 173)
    - Yale University, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 174)
    - "Z" General, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 175)
    - Unidentified, 1951-1955 (Box 9, Folder 176)
  - Printed Matter by Sinclair Lewis
    - Articles from periodicals, printed versions and copies, 1945-1952 (Box 10, Folder 177)
  - Printed Matter about Sinclair Lewis
    - Cabell, James Branch, "Some of us. An essay on epitaphs", 1930 (Box 10, Folder 178)
    - Articles from periodicals, 1945, undated (Box 10, Folder 179)
    - Pamphlets, 1921, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 180)
    - Clippings: From Main Street to Stockholm, 1951-1953 (Box 10, Folder 181-183)
    - Clippings: From the research files of Gladys Almy, 1940-1947 (Box 10, Folder 184)
    - Clippings: miscellaneous, 1930-1953 (Box 10, Folder 185-188)
    - Clippings: miscellaneous (copies), undated (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - Photographs
    - 7 photographs of Sinclair Lewis, 1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 189)
      Also includes letter from Mrs. F. A. Summers
- Other Papers, 1935-1975; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Organized into seven subseries: Writings of Harrison Smith; Writings of Others; Speeches and Interviews of Harrison Smith; Correspondence; Financial Papers and Agreements; Printed Matter; Photographs.
  - Writings of Harrison Smith
    Writings of Harrison Smith consist of typescript drafts, corrected. Some files include related material such as clippings, notes, and correspondence.
    - "Are you an economic illiterate?", 1949 July 18 (Box 11, Folder 190)
    - "George Washington" subject file, 1947-1950 (Box 11, Folder 191)
    - "The Greatest of all Stories", 1947 July (Box 11, Folder 192)
    - Notes, circa 1947 (Box 11, Folder 193)
    - "Women and Literature", undated (Box 11, Folder 194)
  - Writings of Others
    Writings of others consist chiefly of typescript drafts, some corrected, of short works of journalism and literary criticism.
    - Hollander, Lester, "The Tropical Malady of Jack London", undated (Box 11, Folder 195)
    - Lewis, Mrs. C. B., "The North American Indians", undated (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - Transcribed excerpts and quotations on various topics, undated (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - Transcribed excerpts of poems and list of "Characters", undated (Box 11, Folder 198)
    - Unidentified, "Preminger: Drama Without Action," transcribed from the New York Post, 1959 July 12 (Box 11, Folder 199)
    - Wittmer, Sylvia, Poems, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 200)
    - Unidentified, "Re-living the past", 1963 April 6 (Box 11, Folder 201)
  - Speeches and Interviews of Harrison Smith
    Consist of typescript drafts of speeches by, and interviews with, Harrison Smith, addressing social and literary topics. Several speeches address the position of women in society.
    - "The battle may still be lost," for AWA, 1948 October 6 (Box 11, Folder 202)
    - "For young women only: what's wrong with marriage?", undated (Box 11, Folder 203)
    - Nancy Craig Program: Interview with Harrison Smith, transcript, 1947 June 24 (Box 11, Folder 204)
    - Pauline Frederick interviews Harrison Smith, transcript, 1947 January 5 (Box 11, Folder 205)
    - Speech before Altrussa Club, 1948 October 28 (Box 11, Folder 206)
    - Speech made before New York City Committee of National Woman's P---?, 1948 June 17 (Box 11, Folder 207)
    - "This is New York," Bill Leonard reporting. WCBS., 1947 September 11 (Box 11, Folder 208)
  - Correspondence
    Organized into files by topic, with General Correspondence filed at the end.
    - Bodleian Library, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 209)
    - Davies, William H., 1962-1970 (Box 11, Folder 210)
    - Washington, George, 1947-1955 (Box 11, Folder 211)
    - Pacella, Bernard L., 1969 (Box 11, Folder 212)
    - Shaw, George Bernard, 1944-1946 (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - Storck, John, 1953-1954 (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - General, 1940-1969 (Box 11, Folder 215)
  - Financial Papers and Agreements
    - Financial papers and Agreements, 1952-1974 (Box 12, Folder 216)
  - Printed Matter
    - Clippings of articles by Harrison Smith, 1947-1949 (Box 12, Folder 217)
    - Clippings about Jane Reis, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 218)
    - Clippings by Dorothy Thompson, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 219)
    - General Clippings, 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 220)
    - Pamphlets, 1932-1936 (Box 12, Folder 221)
    - Press releases, circa 1946 (Box 12, Folder 222)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of Harrison Smith, circa 1956 (Box 12, Folder 223-224)
    - Portrait of Harrison Smith, negative, undated (Box 12, Folder 225)